FADI GEORGE BASMAJI

85 Torgan Trail, Kleinburg, ON L4H 3X6 | (C) 2898876807 | fadibasmaji@gmail.com | ca.linkedin.com/in/fadibasmaji

Professional Summary

Meticulous Material Science Engineer with a MASc and 2+ years of project engineering experience with a focus on failure analysis and forward-thinking applications for the automotive industry. Proven skills in project management, organization, and communication with a multi-disciplinary team. Adept in problem-solving and applying critical thinking to complex problems, with a keen willingness to learn.

Work History

Manager, Markham Branch Merinos Carpet Inc – Mississauga, ON

2017 to Current

- Develop and implement marketing and business strategies to increase customer base, expand store traffic, and optimize profitability.
- Increased profits through the application of new initiatives by \$3000 in the final quarter of 2017.
- Strong sense of customer care through excellent service and consistently acquiring up-to-date product knowledge, increasing rate of returning customers.
- Complete administration, reports on buying trends and profits to head office, and other managerial duties as needed.
- Maintain outstanding building facilities and support in the selection of merchandise represented.

Materials Testing Technician, Contract Natural Resources Canada – Hamilton, ON

2016 to 2017

- Conducted mechanical analysis for automotive applications with General Motors in a timely and organized manner to meet project milestones.
- Used superior problem-solving and analytical skills to successfully perform engineering calculations to analyze and optimize material testing methodology.
- Designed material testing specifications, managed data collection and analysis, and provided technical input when required.
- Effectively demonstrated strong written and verbal communication skills through the creation of technical reports, memos, summaries, and presentations for clients and project manager.

Graduate Researcher

2013 to 2016

McMaster University - Hamilton, ON

- Co-chaired a research project with Ford Motor Company to reduce vehicle weight and improve fuel economy by up to 5% for next-generation vehicles.
- Used complex problem-solving and critical thinking to develop the baseline plan for the project and constantly adapted to changes in priorities to meet project milestones.
- Designed tests and managed data collection from material property characterization and conducting statistical analysis.
- Communicated project findings through technical reports and presentations to engineering and non-engineering audience to a great deal of success.

Skills

- Failure Analysis
- Metallography & Sample Preparation
- Mechanical Testing
- Material Characteristics of Magnesium, Aluminum and Steel
- MS Office Suite
- Problem Solving & Critical thinking

- Autonomous
- Adaptable & Fast-Learner
- Team Leadership Experience
- Communication Skills
- Project Management
- Organization & Time Management
- Customer Care
- Attention to Detail

Education

Master's of Applied Science: Materials Science and Engineering

2016

McMaster University - Hamilton, Ontario

Thesis title: "Cyclic Fatigue Behavior of Friction Stir Welded AZ-Series Magnesium Alloys"

Bachelor of Engineering: Materials Science and Engineering

2013

McMaster University - Hamilton, Ontario

Professional Development:

- Composite Materials Overview for Engineers at University of Washington and The Boeing Company
- Six Sigma Yellow Belt Certification
- Diploma in Project Management
- Diploma in Supervision
- Introduction to Management: Analysis & Strategies

Volunteer Experience

St. Barsaumo Syriac Orthodox Church

Missions Leader and Youth Board Member (2012 - Present)

- Mediate monthly meetings and advise sub-committees while providing insight and ideas for the future direction of the church youth.
- Support planning of social and spiritual events, budget management and finances of the committee.
- Initiated a Missions committee to address local and global issues by raising awareness of economically disadvantaged people through service learning projects.

Assyrian Chaldean Syriac Student Union (ACSSU) of Canada

Athletic Coordinator for Board of Executives (2017 - Present)

- Monitor budget allocations and expenditures to ensure accurate financial reports are presented.
- Manage and communicate the logistics of events, and implement new initiatives to attract new members resulting in a 50% increase in attendance.

Siempre Juntos Mas Fuerte (SJMF), Canada & Dominican Republic

Group Leader (2015)

- Directed and facilitated all the travel logistics, recruitment, and fundraising events for a 10-day humanitarian mission to build a home for a family.
- Recruited and managed a team of 6 volunteers and organized day-to-day tasks and duties which led to the group completing the project ahead of schedule by 2 days.